<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_5_2">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Advanced search</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <change>
                    <date>2008-07-39</date>
                    <respStmt>
                        <name>EP</name>
                    </respStmt>
                    <item>modified content (typo) </item>
                </change>
                <date>2007-11-14</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (title)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Advanced search allows searching using up to three fields, selectable through
                drop-down lists. Within each field you may specify whether results should match just
                one or all of the search terms, and in the latter case whether or not they should be
                in the specified sequence; it is also possible to specify logical relations (AND,
                OR, and NOT) between the different fields. <xref type="internal" from="p3_8"
                    >Thesauri</xref> are available for all fields other than Title and Registration
                number, and only thesaurus searching is available for Key (click on the 'Thesaurus'
                icon). For the remaining fields (Composer, Opus, Publisher, Publication place, Country, and
                Class) it is possible to search by either using the thesaurus or typing in your
                search terms.</p>
            <p>For textual input, searching is neither case nor accent sensitive (thus 'marsche'
                will find 'Märsche'), and wildcard characters (?, *) may be used: ? substitutes for
                a single character, while * substitutes for any number of characters. Other
                non-alphanumerical characters (e.g. ', +, -) are ignored. For cyrillic entries it is
                possible to paste cyrillic characters into the search box, but it is more reliable
                to use the thesaurus when searching for composers, and transliterations for titles
                (the system adopted is that used in the <title>New Grove Dictionary of Music and
                    Musicians</title>). Results may be limited to a specified range of months and
                years: to select just one year, enter it in the 'From' field and leave 'To' blank.
                If the 'Month' field is not filled in, the whole of the relevant year will be
                searched.</p>
            <p>Results may be sorted by up to three keys selected from the drop-down lists near the
                bottom of the screen (Composer, Date, Opus, Publication place, Publisher, Title; note that
                sorting does not use thesauri but is based on what is in the actual entries). You
                may also specify the maximum total of results to be returned, and the maximum number
                of results to be displayed per page; be careful of choosing 'All' if there is likely
                to be a very large number of results. From any individual item there are links to
                the <title level="m">Monatsbericht</title> page in which it is found, in the form of
                either transcription or facsimile; these will open in a new window. If you wish to
                amend your search rather than start a new one, select 'Back to search' on the
                results page.</p>
            <p>A note on Registration numbers: probably of interest only to specialist users, these
                are found in certain <title level="m">Monatsbericht</title> entries between January
                1831 and April 1838. Not all entries during this period have registration numbers,
                and not all registration numbers are unique. They appear to have been assigned to
                groups of items 'processed' or 'registered' at one time, possibly in connection with
                the Verein der deutschen Musikalienhändler (of which Friedrich Hofmeister was
                Secretary). Items with the same number, and therefore apparently registered at the
                same time, sometimes appear scattered over two or three issues of the <title
                    level="m">Monatsberichte</title>, which suggests that material was not being
                entered into the Monatsberichte in an entirely systematic way.</p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
