<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_5_1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Basic search</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-07-39</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content (typo) </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (links, title, content)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <p>Basic search allows straightforward searching using one or two fields, selectable
                through drop-down lists. It is also possible to limit results to a given range of
                years; if you wish to select just one year, enter it in the 'From' field and leave
                'To' blank. Searching is based on <xref type="internal" from="p3_8">thesauri</xref>
                for all fields other than title; to select a search term click on the thesaurus icon.
                Where two fields are used they are linked by AND (for instance results
                might be limited to just the works of a specified composer published in a specified
                place); if you do not want your searching to be limited in this way, use Advanced
                search instead. When typing in a title, note that searching is neither case nor
                accent sensitive: this means for example that 'marsche' will find 'Märsche'.</p>
            <p>Clicking on 'Search' will generate a list of individual bibliographic items; where
                there are more than ten, use the 'Next' button to see more results, or choose a
                specific range. (Be careful of choosing 'All' if there is likely to be a very large
                number of results.) From any individual item there are links to the <title level="m"
                    >Monatsbericht</title> page in which it is found, in the form of either
                transcription or facsimile; these will open in a new window. If you wish to amend
                your search rather than start a new one, select 'Back to search' on the results
                page. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
