<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_5_3">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Free Text Search</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-07-39</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content (typo) </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-19</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (title)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Free text search allows the location of specific words regardless of the field(s) in
                which they appear, or if they have not been separately coded. This might for example
                apply to dedicatees, librettists, the subjects of illustrations, names or places
                that appear in titles, instruments not included in the Classification lists, prices,
                or any number of technical terms that appear in the <hi rend="italic">Monatsberichte</hi>, such as
                Lichtdruck (a printing technique) or Leporello (a type of binding) All the text in
                the database is searched, including for example Classification headings as well as
                bibliographic items. Thesauri are not used.</p>
            <p>It is possible to search for just one or all of the search terms, and in the latter
                case in the specified sequence or in any sequence. Searching is neither case nor
                accent sensitive (thus 'marsche' will find 'Märsche'), and wildcard characters (?,
                *) may be used: ? substitutes for a single character, while * substitutes for any
                number of characters. Other non-alphanumerical characters (e.g. ', +, -) are
                ignored. For cyrillic entries it is possible to paste cyrillic characters into the
                search box, but it is more reliable to use the thesaurus when searching for
                composers, and transliterations for titles (the system adopted is that used in the
                    <title level="m">New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</title>). Results
                may be limited to a specified range of months and years: to select just one year,
                enter it in the 'From' field and leave 'To' blank. If the 'Month' field is not
                filled in, the whole of the relevant year will be searched.</p>
            <p>Results may be sorted by up to three keys selected from the drop-down lists near the
                bottom of the screen (Composer, Date, Opus, Publication place, Publisher, Title; note that
                sorting does not use thesauri but is based on what is in the actual entries). You
                may also specify the maximum total of results to be returned, and the maximum number
                of results to be displayed per page; be careful of choosing 'All' if there is likely
                to be a very large number of results. Results may include both bibliographic and
                other items (e.g. Hofmeister classification headings); in either case there are
                links to the <title level="m">Monatsbericht</title> page in which the item is found,
                in the form of either transcription or facsimile. If you wish to amend your search
                rather than start a new one, select 'Back to search' on the results page. </p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
