<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_7">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Browsers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-14</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Content modified</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-05-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Content added</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-03-20</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Zaneta Au</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Dummy page</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>


            <p>For this website to be accessible, it must be as easy to use and understand for as
                many visitors as possible. We strive to ensure accessibility by complying with or
                exceeding the recommendations of appropriate industry standards and applicable
                legislation, and we are committed to continually reviewing and improving our levels
                of compliance.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Font Control </head>

                <p>This website offers the option for it to be viewed in different text sizes</p>

                <p>You can  alter the size of the screen fonts using the tools built in to most
                    modern web browsers: </p>
                <list>
                    <item>Internet Explorer (all Windows versions): Go to the 'View' menu, 'Text
                        Size', and select your desired setting. The default is medium.
                        Alternatively, if you have a mouse with a wheel you can hold the CTRL key on
                        your keyboard whilst scrolling up or down with the wheel to alter the text
                        size.</item>
                    <item>Mozilla (i.e. Firefox / Camino, Mac and PC): Go to the 'View' menu and
                        either click the 'Increase Text Size' or 'Decrease Text Size' menu items, or
                        alternatively you can use the CTRL key with the mouse wheel or plus and
                        minus keys to increase or decrease the size.</item>
                    <item>Internet Explorer 5.1 (Mac): Go to the View menu and use the 'Text Zoom'
                        feature.</item>
                    <item>Apple Safari: Go the 'View' menu and use the 'Make Text Bigger' and 'Make
                        Text Smaller' menu items. Alternatively you can use the option key with + or
                        - to increase or decrease the text size.</item>
                    <item>Netscape 7 + (Mac and PC): Go to the 'View' menu and use the 'Text Zoom'
                        feature to change text size. Alternatively you can use the CTRL key with the
                        plus or minus to increase or decrease the size.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Screen Size</head>

                <p>This website will look best at a screen resolution of 1024 x 768 pixels or
                    greater, at a colour depth of 16bit or better. Most laptops, and desktops with a
                    screen size of 17" or larger, will run at this sort of resolution and colour
                    depth. You can find instructions for changing the screen settings of the most
                    popular operating systems below:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <xref type="external"
                            url="http://www.microsoft.com/resources/documentation/windows/xp/all/proddocs/en-us/display_change_screen_resolution.mspx"
                            >Windows XP</xref>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <xref type="external"
                            url="http://windowshelp.microsoft.com/Windows/en-US/help/0386b009-5f30-45c7-80c8-ff0395cc24091033.mspx"
                            >Windows Vista</xref>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <xref type="external" url="http://www.apple.com/support/mac101/customize/4/"
                            >Apple Mac</xref>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Screen Reader Compatibility</head>

                <p>The website supports screen reader programs. We recommend Browsealoud, an
                    application for Mac and PC which can be used with most modern browsers. Once
                    installed, simply click on the logo to switch on the reader and follow the set
                    up instructions. If you have any problems, there is a page which sets out full
                    instructions on installing and uninstalling Browsealoud. When installed,
                    position your cursor at the start of a paragraph and it will start to read
                    automatically. To stop the reader at any point, simply press the Ctrl key.</p>

                <list>
                    <item>
                        <xref type="external" url="http://www.browsealoud.com/page.asp?pg_id=70004"
                            >Browsealoud</xref>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <xref type="external" url="http://www.browsealoud.com/page.asp?pg_id=70059"
                            >Browsealoud full instructions</xref>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Print Version</head>

                <p>This website is designed to print well by default. When you print the website it
                    will automatically be reformatted for a clearer appearance on paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Standards</head>

                <p>This site fully complies with the W3C XHTML 1.0 Standard and will validate.</p>

                <p>The Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) on this site are essentially written according
                    to W3C standards, but we have included additional formatting information which
                    will cause the CSS not to validate. Unfortunately, different web browsers
                    interpret the CSS standard in different ways - often incorrectly - meaning that
                    it is difficult to create stylesheets which both validate against the
                    appropriate standards, but which also allow users to see the website as intended
                    across a wide variety of web browsers and platforms (i.e. Windows, Mac, Linux,
                    etc). We have tried hard to ensure that our users have the best possible
                    experience when browsing this website, irrespective of the sort of browser or
                    computer they prefer to use, but this has meant that we have had to accommodate
                    various browser inconsistencies in our CSS, at the expense of validation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Plugins and Javascript</head>

                <p>No additional plugins are required to use this website. However you will need to
                    make sure Javascript is enabled in your browser:</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Internet Explorer</head>

                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item> Select 'Tools' from the top menu</item>
                        <item>Choose 'Internet Options'</item>
                        <item>Click on the 'Security' tab</item>
                        <item>Click on 'Custom Level'</item>
                        <item>Scroll down until you see section labled 'Scripting'</item>
                        <item>Under 'Active Scripting', select 'Enable' and click OK</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Mozilla Firefox</head>
                    <list type="ordered">

                        <item>Select 'Tools' from the top menu</item>
                        <item>Choose 'Options'</item>
                        <item>Choose 'Content' from the top navigation (or 'Web Features' in Firefox
                            1.0)</item>
                        <item>Select the checkbox next to 'Enable JavaScript' and click OK</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Apple Safari</head>
                    <list type="ordered">

                        <item>Select 'Safari' from the top menu</item>
                        <item>Choose 'Preferences'</item>
                        <item>Choose 'Security'</item>
                        <item>Select the checkbox next to 'Enable JavaScript'</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Browsers</head>

                <p>In order to provide good accessibility some compromises have unfortunately had to
                    be made in terms of full support for certain older browsers which do not support
                    web standards, or support them unreliably or unpredictably. We strongly
                    recommend that you use only the following browsers:</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Windows</head>

                    <list>
                        <item>Internet Explorer 7 (or 6) - available at <xref type="external"
                                url="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/ie/default.asp"
                                >http://www.microsoft.com/windows/ie/default.asp</xref>. Most people
                            have this on their Windows-based PCs already. If you don't have Internet
                            Explorer, or if you have a version earlier than version 6, you should
                            consider obtaining one of the Mozilla browsers (see below) instead,
                            because they are small and quick to download.</item>
                        <item>Mozilla Firefox - available at <xref type="external"
                            url="http://www.mozilla.org/"
                                >http://www.mozilla.org/</xref></item>
                        <item>Netscape 8 (in Internet Explorer or Firefox rendering mode)</item>
                        <item>Opera 8 or above</item>
                    </list>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Apple Mac</head>

                    <list>
                        <item>Apple Safari - available at <xref type="external"
                                url="http://www.apple.com/safari/"
                            >http://www.apple.com/safari/</xref></item>
                        <item>Mozilla Camino / Firefox - all available at <xref type="external"
                                url="http://www.mozilla.org/">http://www.mozilla.org/</xref></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Linux</head>

                    <list>
                        <item>Mozilla Firefox - available at <xref type="esternal"
                                url="http://www.mozilla.org/">http://www.mozilla.org</xref>/</item>
                    </list>

                    <p>The following browsers are not recommended on any platform - they will show
                        the website but may not display the pages optimally:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Internet Explorer &lt; 6 (Not supported on the Mac)</item>
                        <item>Opera &lt; v8 (Mac or PC)</item>
                        <item>Netscape &lt; v8 (Mac or PC)</item>
                        <item>Konqueror (Linux, any version)</item>
                    </list>

                    <p>We appreciate that it might not seem easy or desirable to have constantly to
                        upgrade your browser! If you do have an older browser, or one not on the
                        list above, and you are unable or unwilling to change it, rest assured you
                        will still be able to use the site, but you will not have the best viewing
                        experience. Additionally most accessibility enhancements will not be
                        available to you. Netscape 4 users may only view the site in text-only mode.
                        We therefore again strongly recommend you upgrade your browser. If you'd
                        like to read more about why this is a good idea more generally, visit the
                        Web Standards Project.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
