<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_2">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Classes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-07-39</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content (typo) </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-19</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (title, link)</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Except during the first two years of publication, the Hofmeister <title level="m"
                    >Monatsberichte</title> were divided into what we call Hofmeister
                classifications or more simply Classes: these are a mixture of instrumental/vocal
                and generic classifications, such as 'Music for mandolin', Music for solo piano',
                'Overtures and entr'actes for piano, 4 hands', or 'Part songs with or without
                accompaniment for orchestra, one or several instruments'. (In the first two years
                alphabetical codes were used, broadly mapping onto the later divisions.) This should in
                principle be an extremely valuable means of access to the individual bibliographical
                items, and accordingly we have implemented both Class indices and searches.</p>
            <p>In practice, however, these classifications are less useful and convenient to work
                with than they might have been, for several reasons. As the examples just cited
                indicate, the headings are often unwieldy and sometimes maddeningly inconsistent.
                Moreover they changed over the period covered by Hofmeister XIX, and the various
                classifications used at different times do not map perfectly onto one another. For
                example, the heading 'Music for cello' disappears in January 1872, but the music is
                still there: it is now under 'Music for wind and string instruments'.</p>
            <p>In order to reduce the 800 or so distinct headings found in the <title level="m"
                    >Monatsberichte</title> to a more manageable number, we have created a thesaurus
                that links obviously equivalent headings, but because we have wished to minimize the
                loss of information present in the original, the thesaurus still contains nearly 300
                entries. Moreover, for technical reasons it is only possible for these to be
                displayed in the Class thesaurus window as an alphabetical listing in German, in
                which form entirely different instrumental/vocal and generic classifications are
                mixed up with one another.</p>
            <p>To make it easier to find the Classes you want we have prepared a list of Class
                thesaurus headings, organized according to broader instrumental/vocal categories
                than Hofmeister's, and with English translations. There are also alphabetical
                listings in both English and German. You can download these as either a <xref type="redist"
                    from="pdf/HofmeisterMonatsberichteClasses.pdf">PDF</xref> or an <xref
                        type="redist" from="xls/HofmeisterMonatsberichteClasses.xls">Excel</xref>
                file.</p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
