<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Introduction</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-07-39</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content (typo) </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-19</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (links)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added / modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-03-20</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Zaneta Au</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Dummy page</item>
            </change>

        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Help - Introduction</head>
            <p>While Hofmeister XIX is an indispensable resource for the bibliography of
                nineteenth-century printed music, it is essential to remember that it is a series of
                publisher's catalogues placed online, not a purpose-designed musicological database
                based on independent research. In order to use Hofmeister XIX effectively, it is
                necessary to be aware of the limitations that result from this, as well as the
                inherent complexity of the material.</p>
            <p>Here is a sample Monatsbericht entry:</p>

          <p><figure url="annoshow-buch"></figure></p>
            <p>This may be divided into the following elements:</p>
            <table rend="highlight">
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">Roth (C.)</hi>
                    </cell>
                    <cell>Auswahl guter Orgelcompositionen der vorzüglichsten Componisten.</cell>
                    <cell>Stettin,</cell>
                    <cell>Heerbrandt und Thämel </cell>
                    <cell>1 Thlr. 7½ Ngr. n.</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>In this simple example, the elements are composer, title, place of publication,
                publisher, and price. (Other entries may include additional elements such as opus
                number and key.) Each of these fields, except price, is individually identified in the Hofmeister
                XIX database, and this is what makes it possible to access works by a particular
                composer, and/or published in a particular place, and/or by a particular publisher.
                Sometimes entries include text that does not fall into any of these categories, in
                which case it is not specifically identified in the database, but may still be
                acessed through a free text search. The first of the following two examples
                illustrates this: </p>
            
            
            <p><figure url="annoshow-buch_2"></figure></p>
            
            
            <list>
                <item><hi rend="bold">Kodelski (C.M.)</hi> 2e Concertino p. Violon av. Acc.
                    d’Orchestre. Oe. 2, in D. (Déd. à Mr. Ch. Möser.) Berlin, Trautwein 1 Thlr.</item>
                <item>– Idem av. Acc. de Quatuor. Ebend. 12 Gr.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the first example, 'Oe. 2' is the opus number ('Oeuvre') and 'in D' is the key,
                while '(Déd. à Mr. Ch. Möser.)' is free text. The second example is typical of the
                abbreviations used in the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title>. 'Idem' means that
                this item is also Kodelski's Second Concertino for Violin, but this time for quartet
                rather than orchestral accompaniment; 'Ebend.' (short for Ebenda) means that it is
                also Opus 2 in D, and published by Trautwein in Berlin. An important consequence
                follows from this: if you search for 'Kodelski' and 'Concertino', you will find the
                first entry but not the second. <hi rend="bold">You need therefore to check as a
                    matter of course whether the entry you find is followed by one or more which are
                    also relevant to you, but use these abbreviations</hi>. It should also be
                understood that <hi rend="bold">this is a significant limitation of Hofmeister XIX,
                    in its current form, as a source of statistics.</hi></p>
            <p>Understanding the information in the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title> is the
                key to effective use of Hofmeister XIX, and it is strongly recommended that you look
                closely at some sample pages, using the Browse function in Hofmeister and/or the
                facsimile pages on the <xref type="external"
                    url="http://www.onb.ac.at/sammlungen/musik/hofmeister1.htm">Österreichische
                    Nationalbibliothek</xref> website (to which the Browse pages are linked). It is
                also important to remember that the information in the <title level="m"
                    >Monatsberichte</title> is not invariably accurate. Adolph Hofmeister
                (Friedrich's son) remarked in 1845 that 'printing errors are almost unavoidable in a
                work of this size', while Carl Friedrich Whistling wrote in the preface of the
                second edition of his <title level="m">Handbuch der musikalischen Litteratur</title>
                (the predecessor of Hofmeister's <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title>, published
                in 1817) that</p>

            <p>
                <q>It is unfortunately well enough known that many music publishers’ catalogues,
                    irrespective of printing errors, are rather incomplete and impractically
                    arranged. Here, a first name is missing, there, an opus number; here, the
                    accompanying instruments, there, the number of voices or other important points.
                    Many of the names are wrong; the classification is frequently ludicrous and
                    hinders use; some items are incomprehensibly missing; others, in contrast, which
                    were never published, or have long been out-of-print, are included, etc. Would
                    that this improves in the future.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is also helpful to read the Foreword to Whistling's <title level="m"
                >Handbuch</title>, which clearly sets out the purpose of his catalogue, the criteria
                governing what was and what was not included in it, and the thinking underlying its
                classifications, as well as providing some tips for how to use it. The details had
                changed by the time Hofmeister's <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title> appeared,
                but the basic issues remained unchanged. The Foreword may be found on pp. v-viii of
                the original publication (reprinted in facsimile by Garland Publishing, 1975); click
                <xref type="internal" from="p3_1_1">here</xref> for an English translation by Elizabeth Robinson.</p>
           
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
