<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_4">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Indices</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-07-39</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content (typo) </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-19</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (links)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added / modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-03-20</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Zaneta Au</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Dummy page</item>
            </change>

        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Indices</head>
            <p>Selecting 'indices' enables you to access individual bibliographical items by means
                of an alphabetical listing. Indices are available for Composers, Publishers, Publication places, Classes 
                 (i.e. <xref type="redist" from="pdf/HofmeisterMonatsberichteClasses.pdf"
                    >Hofmeister classification</xref>), and Countries (based on 2006 boundaries).
                Except in the case of Publication place, the procedure is in each case the same: you select
                which index you want to use, then the initial letter of the name you are looking for
                (in the larger indices individual letters are also subdivided), and finally the
                individual index term. In the case of Place, you have the option of doing the same
                ('list'), but you also have the option of opening a map and selecting the place from
                there (by either clicking on a marker or using the drop-down menus). At this point a
                list of bibliographic items corresponding to the specified index term will open;
                these lists are generated on the fly and can be quite lengthy, so response will not
                always be immediate. Clicking on an individual bibliographic item will take you to
                the transcribed <title level="m">Monatsbericht</title> page on which the item is
                found, as when using <xref type="internal" from="p3_3">Browse</xref>, but with the
                item in question positioned at the top of the screen. All indices make use of <xref
                    type="internal" from="p3_8">thesauri</xref>, the purpose of which is to bring
                together equivalent entries (Bizet, Georges; Bizet, George; Georges Bizet, etc). Where,
                exceptionally, you wish to access information without using thesauri, use Advanced
                or Free text Search instead.</p>
            <p>Please note that the map depends on information accessed from Google Maps and we
                cannot guarantee its long-term functioning.</p>



        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
