<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_8">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help - Thesauri</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-07-39</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content (typo) </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-21</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Help -Thesauri</head>
            <p>An important feature of the indices, and of Basic, Advanced, and List searches, is
                the use of thesauri. The purpose of a thesaurus is to establish equivalences between
                different terms corresponding to the same person or thing, so that, for example, 'C
                moll' corresponds to 'Ut mineur': the terms are different but the meanings are the
                same, so normally you will want to find pieces in a given key regardless of whether
                the original publication—and hence the Hofmeister XIX listing—is in German, French,
                or another language. When you use the indices or carry out a thesaurus search, you
                select one thesaurus term, which automatically activates the other, equivalent terms
                in the original <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title>. Thesauri are available for
                Composer, Key, Opus, Publisher, Publication place, Country, and Class, and they are
                automatically used for indices and for Basic search. For Advanced and List search
                you must use thesauri for Key and Country (otherwise you will get misleading
                results), but you can choose whether or not to use them for Composer, Opus,
                Publisher, Publication place, and Class. There are no thesauri for Title or
                Registration number.</p>

            <p>There is a common interface for all thesaurus searches. When you click on the
                'Thesaurus' icon, the relevant thesaurus window opens; enlarge the window if you
                cannot see 'Submit search' at the bottom. This window will contain a complete
                listing of thesaurus terms from which you can select one or more. In the smaller
                thesauri, use the scroll bar to find the term(s) you want; in the larger ones, first
                use the alphabetical index at the top, or type the first few letters into the
                'Starting with' box and click on View. To select a search term, highlight it and
                then click on the 'Insert' button at the bottom of the window; to select multiple
                terms hold down the Control key, or to select a range hold down the Shift key. It is
                not necessary to close the thesaurus window after use; be aware however that if you
                leave a thesaurus window open, you cannot open another. Therefore, if it seems
                impossible to open a thesaurus window, check whether another is already open, and if
                so, close it.</p>

            <p>Certain thesauri require additional explanation. The <hi rend="bolditalic">Opus</hi>
                thesaurus consists of an opus number, followed where appropriate by subdivisions
                within that opus number. The most convenient way to use it is to type the opus
                number into the 'Starting with' box, at which point only entries beginning with that
                number will be displayed. If necessary the process of narrowing down the field can
                continue (e.g. '81a', '5 No. 2'); note that some entries involve ranges, so that you
                might also find Op. 5 No. 2 under '5 No. 1-3'. Posthumous works are identified by
                'posth'. The <hi rend="bolditalic">Key</hi> thesaurus uses a simple code according
                to which 'C+' means C major, and 'C-' means C minor, in each case including the
                equivalents in other languages. 'C' means that the mode is not specified in the
                Monatsbericht entry, which probably means that it is in fact C major. (It follows
                that if you want to search for music in either C major or minor, do not just select
                'C': select C, C+, and C-. Similarly, if you want to be sure of finding all music in
                C major, search for C as well as C+.) In the case of <hi rend="bolditalic"
                >Country</hi>, note that the thesaurus is based on 2006, not historical, boundaries;
                country information is not present in the original Monatsberichte, but has been
                generated by us based on the places of publication. <hi rend="bolditalic">Class</hi>
                refers to Hofmeister classification; this is a sufficiently complex topic to require
                a <xref type="internal" from="p3_2">page</xref> of its own.</p>

            <p>The extent to which we have grouped different terms as equivalent varies from one
                field to another, according to the degree of interpretation involved. In the case of
                key designations there is little difficulty in establishing equivalent terms in
                different languages. In the <hi rend="bolditalic">Publisher</hi> thesaurus we have
                grouped what we believe to be equivalent terms but left names followed by 'in
                Commission' as separate entries: this <xref type="redist" from="pdf/breitkopf.pdf"
                    >extract</xref> from the Publisher thesaurus, showing how we have grouped
                together forty variants of 'Breitkopf &amp; Härtel' and two 'in Comm.', is a
                good illustration of why thesauri are necessary. In the the case of <hi rend="bolditalic">Publication 
                    place</hi> we have grouped terms we believe to be equivalent (e.g. 'Berlin', 'Berl'). For
                both Publisher and Publication place, coding limitations mean that we cannot
                disambiguate entries with identical names even when this information is available
                (thus 'Beadeker' may refer to one of several different publishers, while 'Frankfurt'
                can mean either Frankfurt &lt;Main> or Frankfurt &lt;Oder>). In creating
                these thesauri we have made extensive use of the <xref
                    type="external" url="http://bermudix.ddb.de/dbsm/cgi-bin/gr.pl">Deutsches Buch-
                    und Schriftmuseum</xref> (DBSM) website. 
               </p>

            <p>Because of the sheer numbers involved, it is the <hi rend="bolditalic">Composer</hi>
                thesaurus that presents the worst problems. Sometimes you will see separate
                thesaurus entries for what you feel sure are the same person, for instance, 'Bach,
                C.P.E.', 'Bach, C.Ph.E.', and 'Bach, Carl Philllip Emanuel'. We could have linked
                all of these as being the same person. But what about 'Adam, A.', 'Adam, A.C.',
                'Adam, A.Ch', and 'Adam, Ad.'? There's no simple way to establish whether <hi
                    rend="italic">Monatsberichte</hi> items bearing these names are by the same
                person, and there's no clear dividing line between where we can and where we can't
                be sure of people's identity. We have therefore adopted a conservative policy: <hi
                    rend="bold">the composer thesaurus links those entries which differ in
                    orthography</hi> (such as 'Adam, A.C.', 'Adam, A C', 'Adam, A. C.', 'Adam,
                (A.C.)' or 'A.C. Adam'), <hi rend="bold">but not those entries where substantive
                    interpretation or research would be needed to establish whether or not they are
                    equivalent.</hi> This makes Hofmeister XIX less convenient to use than a modern,
                specifically-researched bibliographical database, but that is one of the limitations
                of using a nineteenth-century publisher's catalogue for a purpose it was never
                designed for. The inconvenience of selecting a number of thesaurus entries to search
                for one composer can however be minimised, though not eliminated, by using the
                facility to select multiple items from the thesaurus window, and the 'Back to
                search' button for repeated searches (which means you do not have to re-enter the
                same search terms each time).</p>
            <p>The complete thesaurus listings can be downloaded from the <xref type="internal"
                    from="p5_2">Download</xref> page. In addition to documenting the equivalences
                built into Hofmeister XIX, these constitute a record of the many variant forms found
                in the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
