<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p3_1_1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Whistling's Handbuch der musikalischen Litteratur: title page and
                foreword</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-21</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Whistling's Handbuch der musikalischen Litteratur: title page and foreword </head>
            <p>Handbook <lb/> of musical literature<lb/> or general systematically arranged<lb/>
                Catalogue<lb/> of printed music,<lb/> also writings on music and illustrations<lb/>
                up to the end of the year 1815<lb/> also listing publishers and prices.<lb/></p>
            <p> Leipzig,<lb/> commissioned by Anton Meysel<lb/> 1817.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Foreword</p>
            <p>The desire to contribute to the promotion and dissemination of music has led us to
                publish this catalogue, originally intended for private use. We of course hoped
                then, when we announced it in advance publicly and invited contributions for it from
                the publishing trade, to list in it all musical items published up to the end of the
                year 1815 which are still obtainable in the shops. Only because several businesses,
                despite repeated urgent requests, did not fully support our wish with notices and
                contributions did we feel compelled to give up our first plan, which was too
                difficult to realise. Therefore we are providing a 'Handbuch der musikalischen
                Litteratur' [Handbook of musical literature] for the friends of music here which
                contains the vast majority and the most noteworthy items from the present-day music
                trade (partly also up to this year) and primarily intended for use in Germany, but
                which may also be used by foreigners because of the chosen orthography and Latin
                alphabet.</p>
            <p>The surnames, first names, titles, prices and publishers are given as clearly as the
                original material and the necessary abbreviations used here permitted. The chosen
                classification, (which is principally based on the number of instruments,) seemed to
                us the most appropriate for general use. The overlapping of individual classes could
                not be entirely avoided here (and indeed probably also couldn't with any other
                classification system used). With frequent use, one will easily learn to use the
                classes which are related to others, and, for example, when one searches for solos
                for one instrument, to search for items under duets for this instrument which have
                an optional accompaniment. An asterisk (*) at the beginning of the line in the first
                64 classes and in 74 and 75 indicate dances, and a dagger (†) indicates variations.
                For various reasons we only wanted to indicate these genres under Solos for the
                Pianoforte in particular classes, but nevertheless to make them easily noticeable
                for enthusiasts. In the 72nd class, a dagger at the beginning of the line indicates
                those pieces which can also be played on the pianoforte; and which have therefore
                been omitted in the 65th class. In the 81st class, the asterisks at the beginning of
                lines indicate those opera excerpts which are incomplete, rather contain just
                individual arias (sometimes fewer, sometimes more) together with the overture.
                Finally, in the 83rd class, those songs which can also be accompanied by guitar are
                indicated with an asterisk before; and those which can be accompanied by harp
                instead of fortepiano have a dagger before, this being omitted later on to save
                space. Further, it should be noted, that in the instrumental music, all works which
                include a guitar part (whether it is the main part or an accompaniment), can only be
                found in the guitar music class. </p>
            <p>The prices are mostly stated in the currency as given on the titles of the printed
                music. Prices set in guldens [guilders/florins] and kreuzers by a few Austrian
                publishers should be understood in Viennese currency, and should by no means be
                regarded as reliable and fixed, as they are frequently changed. The folio size, as
                the most commonly now used for sheet music, is not unusual, however mostly the other
                sizes, when they are known to us, are mainly given before the publication place in
                numbers – 4, 8, 12 or gr. 4, gr. 8 etc. [quarto, octavo, duodecimo or large quarto,
                large octavo, etc.] (or with books, before the publication date).</p>
            <p>In order to avoid increasing the size and price of the publication unnecessarily, we
                have subjected ourselves to certain restrictions, and also made appropriate brevity
                a duty. Namely, in the 'Songs for the pianoforte and for the guitar', we have
                omitted all individual items, those which are too short or too unimportant, likewise
                those in foreign languages, which have been published abroad and are not of prime
                interest to Germans. Furthermore, the 86th class does not contain all the best and
                most important writings, rather just a selection of these, because our main aim was
                to produce a guide with information about printed music of our time such as does not
                exist at the present; and because Herr Dr. Forkel's 'Litteratur der Musik' covering
                the period up to 1792 is excellently suited for information about publications on
                the theory of music and is already well-known to most people who wish to study this
                branch thoroughly. – As regards the abbreviations used here, these are principally
                because 1) we have altered and shortened long and long-winded titles with care. 2)
                Words which occur extremely frequently (e.g. Alto, Basse, Pianoforte, Oeuvre, Opus,
                Violon, Orchestre, pour, avec, Begleitung, Thaler, fuer, das und mit) and names of
                cities and publishers <note>In order to avoid an easy misunderstanding relating to
                    the renowned publishing house of Hummel in Amsterdam, we must note here that
                    this firm is also in Berlin, and despatches its publications from there for most
                    of the German lands and the other countries outside Holland. </note> have been
                abbreviated in an easily understood way already in common use. 3) In some of the
                classes which contain pieces scored for several parts, the accompanying instruments,
                if they are the most commonly found in such genres, have not been listed in every
                entry; users should therefore take into consideration, for example, in the duets for
                pianoforte the entries without listing the accompaniment for pianoforte and violin,
                and in the quartets, the entries without listing the accompaniment for violin, viola
                and violoncello. 4) Entries which have identical titles and are different editions
                of the same work are often typeset in one or more lines running on, particularly
                when the opus number varies from one edition to another, whereby we cannot, however,
                verify whether such editions with identically worded titles are really always the
                same, and not, perhaps, different from each other. For the benefit of those who are
                submitting information about artistic items or wish to have entries listed
                advertising forthcoming publications, most of the opinions contained in the most
                notable, well-known 'Leipziger musikalische Zeitung' [Leipzig Musical Journal] are
                included here in notes under the text, with the addition of the year and page
                number, which readers can refer to, and the asterisks or daggers in the middle or at
                the end of lines (not those at the beginning of lines) indicate these remarks. </p>
            <p>Although we were happy to indicate precisely in every case the original edition under
                the various editions of the same work in accordance with the wishes of several most
                respected gentlemen, we very much regret that because of several difficulties, this
                is now no longer possible. We have, however, mostly placed first those editions
                which seemed to us to be the most legitimate or earliest, but without guarantee. At
                the same time, we should like to point out that in the case of several editions of a
                work, the additional information contained in brackets (e.g. alteration to the opus
                number or the entire title) relate to the edition by the following publisher and
                remain in force until a new bracket occurs. </p>
            <p>We will publish supplements annually which will contain older entries previously
                passed over which belong here, and furthermore and indeed principally,
                newly-published works, and finally notifications of mistakes discovered, and thus
                the Handbuch will become more complete, more useful and more correct. </p>
            <p>While we wish to express our sincere gratitude to all those who have supported us by
                providing reports and contributions, we humbly also ask all those who are able to
                play a role in the perfecting of this work to send us reports, contributions,
                instructions and corrections in future!</p>
            <p>Finally, we ask the reader to forgive any omissions when using this incomplete
                handbook (which – by the way – was compiled in the few leisure hours left after a
                busy working life). Please make allowances for this work, which is the first of its
                kind.</p>
            <p><date>Leipzig, March 1817</date>. </p>
            <p>The Editor. </p>


            

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
