<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p1_6">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Death notice from November 1864 Monatsbericht (pp. 235-6)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-21</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Death notice from November 1864 Monatsbericht (pp. 235-6) </head>
            <p>With great sadness we announce to our business colleagues that this morning at 5
                o’clock our dear father, the founder of our music business <q>Herr Friedrich
                    Hofmeister</q></p>
            <p>died in his 83rd year, from old age. We wish to inform you of this, with deep
                sadness, on behalf of the entire bereaved family.</p>
            <p>
                <date>Leipzig, 30 September 1864</date>
            </p>
            <p>Adolph Hofmeister</p>
            <p>Prof. Dr. Wilh. Hofmeister</p>
            <p>Friedrich Hofmeister, born in Strehla on 24 January 1782, moved to Leipzig with his
                parents at an early age, where his father died shortly afterwards. He began a
                broad-based education at the recently-founded Rathsfreischule [Free Town School],
                spurred on by his own enthusiasm and assisted by the affectionate interest of
                excellent teachers. Men such as Plato and Dolz continued to show an interest in the
                gifted, orphaned boy even after his school days. It was on their recommendation that
                Hofmeister moved into a patrician house for a short period, the head of which chose
                a career as a merchant for him; however, this man’s early death prevented these
                plans being fulfilled. Thus in 1797, almost by coincidence, Hofmeister joined the
                company of Herren Breitkopf und Härtel, already one of the leading businesses, as an
                apprentice.</p>
            <p>Soon after this, he became managing director of the newly-established Bureau de
                Musique, a position which he gave up in 1802 in order to be able to found his own
                business. He chose Riesa for this, where he established himself as a grocer and
                draper.</p>
            <p>After a few years (1805) this small sphere of activity was no longer sufficient for
                him; he moved with his wife and son back to Leipzig in order to sort out and wind up
                the business of his late father-in-law, who had owned a major furniture shop.
                Following this, he returned to the career he had started in, the one which appealed
                to him most. In 1807 he founded his music business, then only the third such in
                Leipzig. He also quickly brought to fruition his first idea of a music lending
                library, a venture which was exceptionally well received.</p>
            <p>His charming personality enabled him to make friendships with young, rising talents;
                publishing their works brought benefit and honour to his publishing house. We are
                reminded of Heinr. Marschner, Friedr. Schneider, Alb. Methfesssel, Aug. Pohlenz etc.
                Similarly, there was also a friendly relationship with Privy Counsellor Ludw.
                Reichenbach in Dresden, who has since become extremely famous, and who introduced
                Hofmeister to the natural sciences. He studied botany until late in life with more
                than amateur enthusiasm, and published exclusively botanical works in the sister
                branch of his company.</p>
            <p>He lived through the toughest time in Leipzig, the year 1813, in the suburbs,
                experiencing various privations and even danger, even if he now only had to be
                concerned for himself; for the previous year he had been widowed and his son had
                been sent to live in a pension out of town. Scarcely had peace been restored in the
                town than he remarried, and his house soon became a popular meeting place for
                musician friends, scholars and others. He needed company, in the best sense of the
                word. Most of the charitable and private societies counted him amongst their patrons
                and most enthusiastic members. He was less involved in the actual public life of the
                town, although he maintained a keen and often active interest particularly in all
                progressive innovations.</p>
            <p>In 1834 he took up residence in the neighbouring village of Reudnitz and later, after
                he had handed his music business over to his two sons, he participated in the
                community life of the village in a senior position with great devotion and fruitful
                activity.</p>
            <p>The last years of his life, which he enjoyed in an exceptionally happy state, were
                full of contented leisure activity with many useful hobbies (including business
                interests) and travels, whilst continuing to work in some enterprises. His
                oft-expressed wish to celebrate his golden wedding was not fulfilled. His wife
                predeceased him by four years. The day that would have been his golden wedding was
                his last day of good health and his life, an active one during which he had seldom
                suffered from poor health, ended after an illness that lasted ten months.</p>
            <p>Hofmeister’s funeral took place at 3 o’clock on the afternoon of 3 October 1864, with
                many of his friends present. The cortege was followed by members of the Apollo
                lodge, of which he had been a member for 39 years, the Reudnitz local council,
                several publishers, members of the gardening association, the polytechnic society
                etc. At the grave, Herr Privy Counsellor Dr. Lucius spoke representing the lodge (in
                verse) and Herr Pastor Schmidt from Schönefeld. May he rest in peace!</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
