<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p1_1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The project</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-19</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-30</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Modified content (links, title)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-02</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added / modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-03-20</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Zaneta Au</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Dummy page</item>
            </change>

        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>In 1829 the Leipzig music publisher <xref type="internal" from="p1_2">Friedrich
                    Hofmeister</xref> began publishing a series of monthly or bi-monthly catalogues
                of printed music, largely but not exclusively based on the products of publishers in
                the German-speaking world. These <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title> at first
                comprised about 2,000 records per year, but by 1900 the annual total had risen to
                13,000, yielding a total of over 330,000 records for the period 1829-1900.</p>

            <p>This constitutes the single most important bibliographical source for the publication
                of music during this period; not only do the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title>
                permit the dating to within approximately eight weeks of any piece of printed music
                listed, but they include books, music periodicals, illustrations, portraits and
                busts of composers, so enabling a comprehensive assessment of the nature and extent
                of music publication at any particular time and place. They are in this way an
                indispensable resource for the study of musical taste and publishing trends in the
                nineteenth century. Further information on the <title level="m"
                >Monatsberichte</title> may be found in '<xref type="redist" from="pdf/elvers.pdf">A
                    survey of the Music Catalogues of Whistling and Hofmeister</xref>' by Rudolf
                Elvers and Cecil Hopkinson, as well as other items listed in the <xref
                    type="internal" from="p5_3">Bibliography</xref>.</p>
            <p>Hofmeister XIX makes this key resource available on the web in a fully searchable
                form; all textual material from the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title> is
                included apart from title pages and advertisements, and the records are linked to
                the high-quality facsimile images of the original <title level="m"
                >Monatsberichte</title> on the website of the <xref type="external"
                    url="http://www.onb.ac.at/sammlungen/musik/hofmeister1.htm">Österreichische
                    Nationalbibliothek</xref>.</p>
            <p>The origins of the project date back to the late 1980s, when the <xref
                    type="external" url="http://www.iaml.info/">International Association of Music
                    Libraries</xref> established a Hofmeister XIX Working Group, but implementation
                began only in 2004, with a grant of £294,784 from the <xref type="external"
                    url="http://www.ahrc.ac.uk/">Arts and Humanities Research Council</xref> under
                its Resource Enhancement scheme. The project was developed and managed by the Music
                Department at <xref type="external" url="http://www.rhul.ac.uk/music/">Royal
                    Holloway, University of London</xref> in association with the <xref
                    type="external" url="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/schools/humanities/cch/">Centre for
                    Computing in the Humanities</xref>, King's College, London</p>
            <p>Funded development of Hofmeister XIX has now finished. It is possible that there will
                at some point be a further phase of development, which would add the predecessors of
                the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title> (the Whistling <title level="m"
                >Handbuch</title> and the <title level="m">Nachträge</title>), so extending the
                resource back to 1817; add the <title level="m">Monatsberichte</title> up to 1945
                (by which time they had become part of the <xref type="external"
                    url="http://www.d-nb.de/eng/service/zd/dnb.htm">Deutsche
                Nationalbibliografie</xref>); and provide enhanced facilities for extracting
                statistical information.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Please note that Hofmeister XIX is not the catalogue of a physical collection of
                music publications, nor is it a list of items for sale. To locate copies of items
                included in it, we suggest you consult the <xref type="external"
                    url="http://www.rhul.ac.uk/Music/Golden-pages/library.html">Karlsruher
                    Virtueller Katalog</xref>, or the list of international music <xref
                    type="external" url="http://www.ubka.uni-karlsruhe.de/kvk/kvk/kvk_en.html"
                    >libraries</xref> on the Royal Holloway Golden Pages.</hi></p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
