<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="beer_eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Hofmeister biography (English)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2007-11-19</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>LK</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>modified content</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2007-04-03</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Created</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Hofmeister, Friedrich</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">This is a translation of an article reproduced from Die Musik
                        in Geschichte und Gegenwart by kind permission of Bärenreiter-Verlag,
                        Kassel. Click <xref type="internal" from="beer_ger">here</xref> for the
                        German original.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">b</hi> 24 Jan 1782, Strehla, near Riesa (on the River Elbe);
                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi> 30 Sept 1864 in Reudnitz, near Leipzig. Music
                    publisher. Hofmeister was orphaned at an early age, attended school in Leipzig
                    and joined the firm of Breitkopf &amp; Härtel as a trainee in 1797. In
                    January 1801 he became an assistant in F. A. Hoffmeister and A. Kühnel's
                    newly-founded Bureau de musique. He moved to Riesa in 1802, where he worked as a
                    grocer, returned to Leipzig in 1805 and in June 1806 rejoined the firm of
                    Kühnel, this time working as a bookkeeper. By 19 March 1807 Hofmeister had
                    founded a music publishing company with a hire department. With its distinctive
                    image, this was able to hold its ground against local competition, and remains
                    in family ownership today. Hofmeister pursued an interest in scientific matters
                    in his leisure time (he also published works in this area), and his residence in
                    Reudnitz with its botanical garden was a meeting place for a circle of friends
                    with both scientific and artistic interests (including Gustav Freytag, Salomon
                    Hirzel and Heinrich von Treitschke). He made considerable efforts to improve the
                    basic organisation of the music publishing trade. Thus, in 1819, he took over
                    the <title level="m">Handbuch der musikalischen Litteratur</title> from Carl
                    Friedrich Whistling as the first comprehensive music bibliography. He was also
                    one of a group of people who were influential in bringing about the Konvention
                    der deutschen Musikverleger gegen den Nachdruck (Convention of German Music
                    Publishers against Copyright infringement) of 23 May 1829 (amended on 12 May
                    1830); Hofmeister was secretary of the association from 1829 to 1852. In the
                    same year he handed over his publishing house to his sons Adolph (1802-1870) and
                    Wilhelm (from his second marriage, 1824-1877, chair of Botany in Heidelberg from
                    1863, later in Tübingen), both of whom had already been involved in the running
                    of the company for many years. He handed over his scientific publishing company
                    to his son-in-law, Ambrosius Abel. The music publishing company was run from
                    1877 to 1905 by the former company secretary Albert Röthing, then by Carl
                    Wilhelm Günther (1878-1956, a grandson of Wilhelm Hofmeister), who moved to
                    Frankfurt am Main in 1952. In Leipzig the company existed as <title level="m"
                        >VEB Friedrich Hofmeister Musikverlag</title> [Volkseigener Betrieb, a
                    state-owned company] from 1952. In 1956 Günther's widow Eva became director of
                    the Frankfurt company, later running it with her adoptive son Karlheinz
                    Schwarze, who became sole proprietor on her death (1964) and moved the company
                    to Hofheim in the Taunus. After the restitution of the Leipzig company to
                    Schwarze (1992), the whole company returned to the place where it had been
                    founded (1996); since 2002, the sole proprietor has been Stefanie Schwarze.</p>
                <p>Hofmeister acquired publishing companies including Whistling in Leipzig (1829),
                    Laue and Christiani in Berlin (1832 and 1840) and Brüggemann in Halberstadt
                    (1832). In more recent times, Hofmeister has acquired the rights in many works
                    published by Ernst Challier and Carl Merseburger. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Publications</head>
                <div>
                    <head type="sub">I. Specific Catalogues</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl><title level="m">Thematisches Verzeichniss der Compositionen für
                                Instrumentalmusik welche von den berühmtesten Tonsetzern unsersers
                                [sic] Zeitalters erschienen sind. Seitenstück zu dem Handbuche der
                                musikal. Literatur. 15 Heft Louis van Beethoven</title>, Leipzig, 1819
                            (further vols. not published.)</bibl>
                        <bibl><title level="m">Thematisches Verzeichniss von CLXXII vorzüglichen
                                Sinfonien und Ouverturen für Orchester welche von berühmten
                                Tonsetzern unseres Zeitalters gedruckt erschienen sind,</title>
                            Leipzig, 1831</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="sub">II. Bibliography</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl><title level="m">Handbuch der musikalischen Litteratur [from 1821:
                                Literatur] oder Allgemeines systematisch geordnetes Verzeichniss
                                gedruckter Musikalien auch musikalischer Schriften, mit Anzeige der
                                Verleger und Preise, 2nd to 8th supplement (Nachtrag),</title>
                            Leipzig, 1819-1825 (each with a foreword by Hofmeister; the 1st edition
                            [1817] and supplements 1, 9 and 10 were published by C.F. Whistling, who
                            was also editor under Hofmeister); repr. ed. by N. Ratliff, N.Y. 1975; </bibl>
                        <bibl>A. Hofmeister edited the work from the 2nd supplementary vol. (<title
                                level="m">Ergänzungsband</title>) up to the 2nd ed. (1834) in his
                            father's publishing house, as well as editing the
                            Musikalisch-literarischer Monatsbericht neuer <title level="m"
                                >Musikalien, musikalischer Schriften und Abbildungen</title>,
                            founded in 1829 by Whistling, from 1834.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p>Hofmeister's name is identified with the consistent, systematic and complete
                        bibliography of musical works (even those works with prices <hi
                            rend="italic">"set as low as just 4 Groschen or less"</hi>; preface to
                        the 2nd supplement, 1819, p. [III]). The foundations which he established
                        continue to be of importance to the present day, in that they established an
                        awareness of the need for music-bibliographical work. Even in the years in
                        which he did not function as editor and publisher of the <title level="m"
                            >Handbuch</title>, Hofmeister, later with his son Adolph, emphatically
                        supported the work (in the preface to the 2nd edition, p. 7, Whistling
                        writes of the <hi rend="italic">"continual assistance of the Herren
                            Hofmeister"</hi>). Adolph Hofmeister assumed responsibility in 1834 and
                        continued it in the spirit of his father and Whistling (see <hi
                            rend="italic">Tradition und Gegenwart</hi>, 1957, pp. 37-39 for
                        information on its further development). </p>
                    <p>Friedrich Hofmeisters contribution to bringing about the agreements between
                        German music publishers in the years 1829 and 1830 was without doubt
                        considerable. As early as 1823, in the face of the ever-increasing number of
                        unauthorised reprints of other publishers' works, he had suggested a
                        "voluntary, tacit agreement of all parties" (<title level="m"
                        >Handbuch</title>, 6th supplement of 1823, preface, pp. IV-V), however, it
                        was A. M. Schlesinger above all, who invited the Leipzig publishers,
                        including in particular C. F. Peters, to Berlin to participate in
                        discussions (see A. Beer 2000, pp. 67f.); as secretary of the Verein der
                        Musikverleger for many years, Hofmeister made a great contribution to the
                        cause of music publishing.</p>
                    <p>From the very beginning, the publishing house specialised in piano and guitar
                        music, together with Lieder and teaching material. Alongside works by the
                        leading composers of his generation, Hofmeister also published younger, less
                        well-known composers. The company published the first editions by composers
                        including Marschner (almost his entire output), Schumann (op. 3-5, 7, 10,
                        105), Clara Wieck (op. 1-7), Mendelssohn (op. 12), Weber (op. 10), as well
                        as works by Czerny, Fürstenau, Henselt, Kirchner, Liszt, Löwe, Methfessel,
                        Romberg and J.C.F. Schneider. The most important publications of the later
                        period include Mahler's 2nd Symphony (1897) and Hans Breuer's <title
                            level="m">Zupfgeigenhansl</title> (1909). At present (2002) an extensive
                        publication programme includes critical first and new editions, teaching
                        materials, flexible ensemble music, choral works, an increasing number of
                        works by contemporary composers and series of books. Hans Rheinfurth is
                        preparing a complete publisher's catalogue for the 19th century.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="sub">Documents</head>
                    <p>D-L Esta (Saechsisches Staatsarchiv, Leipzig) material from Friedrich
                        Hofmeister Musikverlag (archival material from 1800 to 1923, mainly from the
                        period 1830-1850; see also Beer 2000, p. 486)</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="sub">Literature (Selection)</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl><title level="m">Tradition und Gegenwart, Fs. zum 150jährigen Bestehen
                                des Musikverlages Friedrich Hofmeister</title>, Leipzig 1957. </bibl>
                        <bibl>H.-M. PLESSKE, <title level="m">Bibliographie des Schrifttums zur
                                Gesch. deutscher und österreichischer Musikverlage, in: Beiträge zur
                                Gesch. des Buchwesens 3</title>, 1968, 135-232 (178f.).</bibl>
                        <bibl>R. ELVERS/C. HOPKINSON, <title level="m">A Survey of the Music
                                Catalogues of Whistling and Hofmeister, in: Fontes Artis
                            Musicae</title> 19, 1972, 1-7. </bibl>
                        <bibl>N. RATLIFF, <title level="m">Handbuch der musikalischen Litteratur: a
                                Reprint of the 1817 Edition and the Ten Supplements,
                            1817-1827</title>, N.Y. 1975. </bibl>
                        <bibl>D. W. KRUMMEL, <title level="m">The Beginnings of Current National
                                Bibliography for German Music</title>, in: <title level="m">Fs. R.
                                S. Hill</title>, ed. C. S. Bradley, Detroit 1987, 307-329.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L. WEINHOLD/A. WEINMANN, <title level="m">Kataloge von Musikverlegern
                                und Musikalienhändlern im deutschsprachigen Raum 1700-1850</title>,
                            Kassel 1995, 51f. </bibl>
                        <bibl>T. WIDMAIER, <title level="m">Der dt. Musikalienleihhandel. Funktion,
                                Bedeutung und Topographie einer Form gewerblicher Musikdistribution
                                vom späten 18. bis zum frühen 20. Jh.</title>, Saabrücken 1998. </bibl>
                        <bibl>A. BEER, <title level="m">Musik zwischen Komponist, Verlag und
                                Publikum,</title> Tutzing 2000. </bibl>
                        <bibl>FR. KAWOHL, <title level="m">Urheberrecht der Musik in Preußen
                                (1820-1840)</title>, Tutzing 2002.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p>AXEL BEER (translated by Elizabeth Robinson)</p>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
